Heat.
[music]
>> [music]
>> I just want to tell [music] you it's not
even over. As long as [music] there's
eyeballs still inside my head, I will
see evil.
Fear [music] evil.
See evil.
[music] Fear evil.
Here evil.
[music]
>> We are spending over $10 million a year
to take down graffiti. I just want to
tell [music] you it's not even over as
long as there's eyeballs still inside my
head. [music]
>> You see shootings and things like that
happening in our city, they start from
tagging and defacing people's problems.
>> Evil.
[music]
Having caused thousands of dollars in
graffiti related damage over the last
year and a half, Ralph Medal was
sentenced to 8 years in prison. Put up a
tag and I have to walk down the street
to look at. Is that a crime against me?
>> Here's here's the deal. Um,
we're we're looking for this vigilante
guy who who does
>> all this silver silver spray paint all
around downtown campus and shadic area.
>> Who does that? Is it one guy? Just one
guy?
>> I think it's one guy, but it could be
could be more than one. Probably one
guy.
>> All right.
>> So, if I give you a couple bucks and
will you keep an eye out for us? And if
you ever
>> see a guy with a spray paint can, what
do you want me to do to him?
>> Don't do anything. Just see what he
looks like. Yes. See what he
>> Maybe ask him what he's doing or why
he's doing it.
>> Okay. I'll try I'll try to get his name.
Maybe I'll ask him his nickname.
>> Yeah.
>> Why is it just damaging things?
>> Yeah, that's what we want to know.
>> Since the first [music] humans etched
images onto cave walls, others have been
there to erase their work. Whether
because of annoyance, [music]
fastidiousness, or simply duty, one
man's mark has always [music] been
another's blight to eradicate. In the
1970s, graffiti exploded into a cohesive
movement in Philadelphia, New York, and
other US cities. Subway trains were a
favorite of graffiti writers because
they carried names and messages
throughout the city. Some felt
threatened by [music] the markings and
in 1989 the New York authorities decided
to draw the line. They did what [music]
many thought was impossible. They rid
the trains of graffiti nearly
completely. The act of eliminating a
piece of graffiti is now known as
buffing and the people who do it as
buffers. New York's clean subway trains
[music] were the first milestone in the
history of buffing. As graffiti has
spread to major cities and small towns
throughout the world, many different
strategies and technologies have been
employed by the buffers. Some cities
have nearly eliminated graffiti, often
through strict laws and buffing
regimens. Buffers are usually employed
by the city [music] or by a property
owner and held to certain standards. But
in recent years, we've seen a new
phenomenon. Vigilante [music] buffers
now take on the battle against graffiti
as a personal crusade and see breaking
the law as the only effective way to win
the fight.
>> Are you guys graffiti removal people?
>> Yes, we are.
>> Wonder if you guys might have heard of
someone called the Silver Circle. He was
a famous graffiti buffer out here. His
name was Ron Ingman. Portland, Oregon.
>> Oh. Oh, yeah. Yeah, yeah, yeah.
>> The Silver Circle vigilante was in inner
city Portland in the suburbs. I mean, it
seemed like he buffed faster than the
city. He was on top of the whole [__]
game. You could not get [__] up at all
without him dissing it within 24 hours.
>> I mean, the word vigilante is just
great, isn't it? And look at the popular
movies, right? It's always kind of that
rogue guy, Bruce Willis or something.
>> Who are you?
>> The vigilante is a chronic figure. Comes
up in popular culture a great deal. But
it's a fantasy that an individual could
write the wrongs of society. You know,
it's like the, you know, the classics
are Charles Bronson and Clint Eastwood.
>> It's the law. Well, then the law is
crazy.
>> Bad people are doing bad things to
innocent people, and one guy
can stop that.
>> They were rocking an HOD throw um on a
truck in Southeast Portland. Car drove
past, [__] hit the block, looped
around, and dude came running out, man.
[music] An old man with a [__] big
gray beard. He hit Grease twice on the
side of his head with a hammer and
basically they just ran. You know,
>> if you define a vigilante as somebody
who is so motivated by their values that
they begin to operate outside of the
confines of legality or of mainstream
networks of communication, if that's
what a vigilante is, then a graffiti
writer is a vigilante, a social
vigilante. On the other hand, some
vigilantes do want to get rid of
graffiti or clean up the community or
make it free of graffiti. And I think
they're both reaching out in
non-normative ways.
>> You know, human beings have been making
marks uh that we know of uh for 45,000
years. For the most part, graffiti is a
way of saying something and it's driven
by a creative urge within somebody. It's
an outlet for creative expression. This
is a different kind of expression. It's
almost a an expression of a repression,
of pushing down, of covering, of
eliminating.
>> Silver and gray, I think, are used here
because it's the absence of any color.
It's it it is a true anti-statement,
anti- art. It's like a black hole in the
middle of something. They mean less than
anything. I mean, less than nothing. He
got busted at least six to eight times.
[music] First five times he got let
loose. They were just like, "Okay,
you're a citizen and [music] you're
trying to do the right thing and you
want to get rid of these like punk
graffiti writers and [__] cuz nobody
likes graffiti writers." And so, you
know, they kept letting him off, but
they kept saying, "Oh, but you need to
stop doing that." And he didn't stop.
When he finally got like busted, busted,
arrested, put in jail, I was stoked. You
know what I'm saying? It's only right.
He was going out in the late nights just
like we were and spray painting stuff.
Vigilantes are kind of this populist
movement in that they see themselves as
beyond politics. They see themselves as
distrustful of yet supportive of
society. They see themselves as beyond
but part of government. And to have that
kind of hubris to believe what you're
doing every day is somehow going to save
some segment of society really makes you
an admirable slashc crazy individual.
>> We're rolling here.
>> So uh who's the silver buff?
Wow. [sighs and gasps]
The Silver Buff
is a anti-graffiti vigilante vandal.
That's how I like to put it. I started
noticing his work a couple years ago. I
could tell his [music] buffing work was
not the city. It was the work of a
vigilante. For somebody to go out and
essentially do graffiti to eliminate
graffiti seems very hypocritical,
[music] very paradoxical to me.
Graffiti represents a voice, a free
voice. And that's extremely important to
have in any society to have an [music]
outlet where you can express yourself
without any control and be heard by the
people around you.
I think these vigilantes are trying to
maintain the visual and aesthetic status
quo. They only want you to see the
officially sanctioned messages. They
don't want any alternative [music]
voices to be heard. And that's why I see
it as something very sinister and very
wrong, something that I'm dedicated to
fighting against.
I got Nate involved and we found an
intersection up in North Berkeley where
he seemed to be especially active. This
foam booth right here is what I would
call his personal playground. It was
once like this blue and over time last
couple years it's become completely
silver. This sticker is going to be put
on the phone booth and then he's going
to come and paint it.
If two people approach him with a
camera, he's done. He's either going to
run for it [music] or he's just going to
[__] give up.
How's it going?
>> You guys got going on tonight?
>> We're doing a little film project.
>> Film project? Yes, sir. That's what we
got the caller out. Who you guys working
for?
>> And And why are you guys doing it at
night?
>> We're just doing sort of a nighttime
lurking film.
>> That's good.
>> I had the camera up and you had the
binoculars.
We were both looking looking [laughter]
through.
>> Everything came out clear.
>> Yeah.
>> I recommend not filming right now at
this time. We just had two robberies
>> really
>> via, you know, threat and all night long
we're looking for people who are
suspicious in vehicles walking around
>> and this is very suspicious.
>> We wouldn't be filming ourselves robbing
>> anybody.
>> Of course not. Well, like I explained to
you, staking out, doing some
reconnaissance. Okay, these are things
that we look out for. This is not
normal. Okay,
>> understood. We're out of here.
>> Okay, I appreciate gentlemen, for
cooperation. Get your stuff back.
The broken windows theory introduced by
James Q. Wilson and George Kelling
[music] in 1982 has become the most
prevalent rationale for a vigilant
response against graffiti. The theory
[music] states that minor quality of
life crimes such as vandalism, public
drinking, [music] panhandling, and
homelessness contribute to a sense of
lawlessness and thus to more serious
crimes. The theory was most famously
implemented by police chief Bill Bratton
and Mayor Rudolph Giuliani during the
1990s [music] in New York City. Many see
New York's drop in crime as concrete
proof supporting the [music] theory,
while many others question its logic and
priorities. The broken windows theory
appeals to middle class fears [music]
about street crime and decay while
completely ignoring structural and
economic forms [music] of damage and
corruption.
There was no bias involved in what
George Kelling and I wrote. We were not
interested in the structure of American
society or class differences or racial
differences. We were making an argument
that the police should spend a lot of
their resources making communities feel
good and look good because when you do
that, the public responds very
effectively. If you improve public
order, this will have the effect of
driving down the crime rate because with
more decent people on the street and
fewer criminals on the street, the crime
rate will go down because the good
people are controlling the streets.
Graffiti is important symbolically
because graffiti conveys the sense that
decent people do not control the
neighborhood and that is what makes it
so unsettling. Once that was pointed
out, public authorities took it very
serious. Now, it's an uphill struggle,
but they've made this commitment, and I
think it it is a healthy commitment. Who
decides what constitutes order or
disorder? Very important question.
There's no rule book that tells you how
to do these things. You have to have a
conversation. All of the serious studies
I know about supporting the broken
windows theory, now in time, somebody
will come up with a study that doesn't
support it. That's the nature of social
science. You just go back and forth on
these things. But I'm confident
personally that what George and I did
was the right thing and most people
believe it. Don't put graffiti in my
area. Maybe one idiot would do it.
In 1991, there was the Rodney King
beating followed by the riots in 1992
when the officers were acquitted. What
happened was I sold carpet. I [music]
was in Korea Town that day. The Koreans
were arming themselves. It was crazy.
So, I decided screw this. As the guy
progressed into the city, some guys went
up in our neighborhood actually looting.
I have this little tool that uh it
punctures people's tires. people that
were taking stuff and looting and
putting them in their car. I started
puncturing their tires, flattening their
cars, didn't deal with this guy. I was
breaking out people's windshields. I
was, you know, because they're put TV
sets in their cars. They put the TV set
in the car, broke the glass out. Then I
was drawn to this one guy's car. He had
looted some liters of Coke from the
7-Eleven. He started sticking doaggs in
them and soaking the rags in gas. I
walked up to him. I says, "You are not
setting this [__] building on fire. I
don't give a [__] who you are. You're
getting the [__] out of here right now."
Pulls up his thing. He's got two guns.
So I wound up testifying against this
guy and they didn't convict him.
>> They did.
>> Did not. He
>> got off.
>> Got off. This guy was such a hardcore
gang member. I was supposed to be in the
witness protection plan. The guy in the
FBI said, "Well, yeah, not only is he um
not guilty and we can't retry him again,
but we don't have any more money for the
witness protection program, so you're
going to have to stay in Los Angeles."
For two weeks, I didn't go to work. I
slept in a bathtub in my house. [__] the
system.
In 1993 [music] when our neighborhood
they decided to take the neighborhood
back. A meeting was called at someone's
house and they had these eight things on
a a list on a wall. So the last thing
was graffiti. So they said, "Okay, you
[music] in the back uh you got
graffiti." So I laughed. I'm like,
"Well, [__] this is going to be easy
cuz there's no graffiti." So then I went
out the next day to the alley and the
whole thing was covered. And I'm like,
"Holy [__] what am I getting myself
into?"
>> See, now see over here on [music] this
thing, see if they got stickers all over
the sign. That's like that's like so
simple to take care of that. I got up at
3:00 and 4:00 in the morning. I'd go
out, paint graffiti, come back, change
my clothes, shower, go out to work at
6:00, come back from work at 6:00,
barely grab something to eat with my
wife, say hi to my kids, go back out
till midnight. That went on for probably
13 years.
>> They hate this because it's [__] like
this. And and that's the problem. That's
the problem.
>> I [music] had a vision that when I got
older, there would be something. thing.
I didn't know what it was, but it would
involve colors and a lot of just [music]
really weird, out of the box creative,
funky stuff. So, when I got into this
graffiti thing, I said, "This is the
vision I had when I was a kid. This is
what I want to do." A lot of things in
my life were completely out of control,
and now I totally control something that
is, man, it's almost better than an
orgasm.
>> We missed him. It was the only night we
didn't go out in the last several days.
It was raining and I didn't think he was
going to go and we have no idea what
time it was at. I'm committed to make
sure he's covered every night from now
on. One of the things about doing this
is you start thinking everybody is the
guy you're looking for when you're out
on the street. I just saw some guy on a
bike getting off his bike a couple times
and going over to some phone booth or
something.
So, I'm going to go check him out again.
see if he's up to no good.
>> He's been active two [music] nights in a
row. So, what we're going to do is we're
going to go up to the location. We're
going to park this thing and we're kind
of just going to do some lurking.
[music]
life.
>> He hit it. Yeah, he did. He hit it. He
hit the spot. Friday night, Saturday
morning, sometime,
>> we have no idea exactly.
>> Sometime sometime between 3:00 a.m. and
7:15 a.m. Our little digital camera kept
running all night, amazingly for more
than 2 hours. Did
>> for hours.
>> It didn't rain all night. [laughter]
>> Yeah,
>> it did. This is what we got here. This
is what he does. This is what he just
did. There you go. There's the evidence.
>> He even did that. Look at that.
>> He did. He did.
>> I just saw that guy take a picture,
dude.
>> Did he?
>> Yes.
>> He's reading the paper.
>> I don't give a [__] I just saw him take
a [__] picture.
>> You're not just seeing things, though,
right?
>> I don't know.
I don't know what I'm doing anymore.
[snorts] I don't know.
>> All right.
>> There was the guy on the bike that was
totally [__] covered in silver paint.
>> It could have been silver. It was the
light colored.
>> That guy [__] was taking a picture of
this trash can though right here.
>> Really?
>> I mean, when I when when I told you
about that.
>> Yeah.
>> All right. [__] it.
[music]
>> How you doing? Good. I'm wondering if
you've noticed any of the silver uh
handle going on over here.
>> What?
>> Have you noticed any of the silver spray
paint
>> on any of the spray painting things?
>> Yeah, all the silver.
>> I thought I saw you taking a picture or
something.
>> I don't like the camera.
It started at 3:03 a.m. and the
recording is an hour and 17.
It's just an hour and 17 minutes.
>> It's got to be longer than that.
>> I thought it was still on.
>> It was, man.
>> What?
>> No.
>> Is that a person? I thought I thought
there could be a person in the dark
there, but I don't think so.
>> It's not cool, dude.
>> It isn't that cool.
>> You know, graffiti when you're an
outsider, it's hard to understand. You
see a lot of scroll, what looks like
scrawling or scribbling to you, and you
may see some stuff that's colorful, but
it's [music] really hard to read unless
you've been around it for a long time.
Because it's hard to read and hard to
understand, people are very threatened
by it. I've now put out a book about uh
the Bay Area graffiti culture, the first
book about the Bay Area graffiti
culture. I think of San Francisco as a
place that generally has embraced
alternative cultures and alternative
[music] ways of looking at the world and
I see that changing a little bit. Well,
this is a spot that in the graffiti
world was called Tire Beach.
Essentially, this whole park and this
whole area was a major graffiti location
for quite a [music] few years. Was a
place where generally speaking, police
did not bother people doing the
graffiti. If you have a wall that's
allowed to run for many, many years, you
end up with an accumulation of greater
and greater quality because the good
stuff lasts and the bad stuff [music]
gets gone over. When I was just
beginning to get interested in graffiti,
I was blown away when I walked into this
[music] park. I can leave my house, 10
minutes later, I can go to this cool
park by the bay and I can see all this
amazing art [music] and now it's just a
big green wall. It's completely ugly by
comparison and doesn't do anything to
make me [music] want to be in this park.
It was the usual kind of graffiti
removal theory. If people are allowed to
paint in one area, even if it's not
disturbing anybody, the culture is
invigorated. So, if you stamp it out
here, you know, you're contributing to
the demise of the culture.
>> Graffiti is not street art. It is a
crime to the vandal. Now is the time to
give up your life of graffiti vandalism
and channel your love of art into legal
ways of expressing it. For me, the
discussion doesn't end when you say it's
illegal. In fact, that's kind of where
the discussion begins. When you see
these anti-graffiti [music]
bits of propaganda, video, or some
pamphlet, what they always emphasize are
the tags, the stuff that's done over
windows or in some place that people
find very [music] offensive. Endlessly
connecting graffiti to gangs, endlessly
connecting graffiti to larger criminal
activity, to destructiveness, to
violence. They're often wildly
exaggerated when city officials discuss
how to address graffiti or why it needs
to be addressed.
>> Fundamentally, graffiti is disrespect.
It's disrespect for people. It
propagates violence, misogyny.
>> This is the beginning of people becoming
hardcore criminals. When you see
shootings and things like that happening
in our city, they start from tagging and
defacing people's property and they just
keep on growing and growing and then we
start seeing a lot of murders in the
city. You start by just painting
somebody's property, you know, do a
little bit of that, you know, maybe
start doing a little drugs, you know,
start getting a little high, but then
you graduate to uh robbery, you graduate
to shooting. You put that tag up today,
hopefully by before the end of the day,
it's gone. We're now empowering
residents and people who have joined our
programs to buff out any graffiti that
they see.
>> That's San Francisco Green right there.
>> That's Noodle Green.
[laughter]
the city of San Francisco.
>> It's easy for me to take this, hand it
to you, and say, "When you see graffiti,
just spray it out."
>> The city has been involved in this kind
of crackdown against graffiti for a good
5 years at least. The result of the
campaign has been, I would say,
virtually total [music] success from the
point of view of the people trying to
eliminate graffiti. That is both the
culture and the graffiti itself have
been basically eliminated. Along with
the intense buffing activity, [music]
they put in place a variety of laws that
forced property owners to clean up their
own graffiti. That had a couple of
effects. One is to build a kind of
resentment against the graffiti culture
and against graffiti because property
owners felt more victimized by graffiti,
I think, than they used to. You know,
you're forced to pay money to clean it
up or be fined.
I don't want to go out into a city
that's full of [music] gray and green
drab walls. I mean, that sort of makes
me feel like I'm living in a I don't
know, the former Soviet Union or
something like that. I mean, I want to
see walls that are filled with color,
that are filled with personal
expression. And [music] graffiti is part
of that equation. And that's one of the
reasons I love living in a city.
>> What if I went out and buffed graffiti
with the wrong color and I made more of
a mess than it was already there?
>> Who says? Who says? Because a lot of
people that let me tell you I do it as a
job and a lot of people they don't even
care about the color. Long as they get
the graffiti off their building they're
happy with respecting other people's
property. That's the that's the main
gist. You're an American citizen in a
society that's already been formatted.
You're in a culture of America and
America if if you think for one second
that you're going to change that because
America's about advertisement. I grew up
I have respect for society. I don't I
don't go tagging on anyone's building. I
never tagged in my life. I never did cuz
I respect other people's property like
my dad taught me. graffiti is left as a
permanent monument. Um, mainly to
promote the defacer. That's all it is.
It's it's teenage energy to show guys,
show their buddies how brave they are to
each other. That's all it is.
>> That's the thing that makes it so hard
to talk to folks. You guys have your set
opinions already. Isn't it my job is I
vandalize vandalism.
>> But also the idea of the whole the whole
terminology of
>> just going to scratch the lens a little
bit with my initials. Do you mind?
>> Hey man, don't touch the lens with the
key.
>> Hey, wait. What's the problem?
>> The [__] are you doing, man?
>> I'm defacing property. It's a public
expression. It's a public expression.
You got to prioritize, man. Why are you
so concerned about the lens of the
camera? Prioritize,
>> dude. Excuse me.
>> You seem to be emotionally distraught
and you need to get some help.
>> What's your name?
>> Why don't you guys settle down?
[music]
>> Yeah.
>> [music]
[music]
>> Hey. Here's reality here. We have a
problem in this city. The bottom line is
if city had something in place, I
wouldn't be doing this.
after Katrina, you know, we were a
pretty screwed up city and it's like,
yeah, you know, it's the the Katrina
story again, but I mean, it really was.
My goal was to make signs to put up
around town to remind people why New
Orleans was such a great place. We had a
lot of people spray painting stuff on
their house like, "I'll be back." I was
driving one day and I saw Nola Rising
spray painted on the side of a building
and I was like, "Oh, you know, it's such
an awesome message." And so I just took
it and ran and it grew into a whole
group and organization. People could
really spread their own version of
positivity.
>> I think this city is full of vibrant
life, vibrant music. Everything's
colorful and lively. [music]
And to have everything
grayed out is just a sad state of
affairs. So I was trying to find this
guy, this notorizing guy. I eventually
did find him. We kind of worked together
and did this story and a lot of it had
to do with Fred and what Fred was doing
to Michael Dingler's work.
>> No Rising was prosecuted for doing over
a thousand different uh uh pieces of
cardboard on telephone poles. I I I
don't want to be associated with people
that are out there doing vandalism.
>> You think that that's vandalism?
>> Hi, this message is for Fred Ratkkey. My
name is Nate Walman and I am working on
a documentary project concerning the
lives of graffiti abatement
professionals such as yourself. You or
someone of interest to us. Was wondering
if maybe you'd like to meet up for an
interview and talk about some of your
techniques. There's the gray. There's
the evidence.
>> Is that Ry? That's [__]
Let's get out.
>> Mr. Raky, sir.
Sir, I came all the way from California
to interview you. I'm doing a
documentary on graffiti.
>> You're doing it the wrong way.
>> We've been trying everything.
>> Doing it the wrong way, sir.
>> How can we talk with you?
>> Loving you.
Loving you
is like staring at my reflection.
[music] Two crazy dimensions.
Reaching towards ascension.
Sitting in [music] detention,
twisting your dimension.
You wanted more attention, [music] but
the forces
here are drunk.
They lasted [music and singing]
for so long.
The future
at this
where I live.
[music]
Hey, what's up? [music]
>> We got him.
>> What do you mean?
>> He came around 6:45. I got him. I saw
the footage. We [__] got him.
>> Oh my god.
Heat. Heat.
Excuse
[music]
me, sir. Are you the person who uh does
all this community service?
>> No,
>> you're not.
>> I don't know what you mean.
What? What do you mean?
>> You do all this community service. You
paint over things. You pick up garbage.
>> Well, I do some of that. Yeah.
>> Yeah.
>> So,
[music]
you did you notice?
>> No, I didn't know that.
>> Oh, well, come on up the street. I think
there's probably still some left from
yesterday. You've heard of rappers.
Well, there's slappers.
>> Slappers.
>> Slappers. Slappers slap um their
identity on every, you know, every
conceivable place.
>> There's uh there's three 3,000 of these
in Berkeley.
>> 3,000 of those poles.
>> Yeah. General Order 95 rule 31.0 says uh
thou shalt not attach to consider
unauthorized attachment. Nobody seems to
know that.
>> And how long have you been doing this?
Early 90s, I guess.
>> Early 90s. Wow.
>> Well, that's somebody's ID identity.
>> Erase it.
>> Cover thing.
>> How many mornings a week do you do this?
It's like a full-time job almost.
>> No. No. Almost every morning. This is a
very useful thing. This used to be
square on the top.
>> Yeah.
>> Did you go to Cal?
>> Oh, yeah. I was in city planning.
>> Ah.
>> Believe it or not, but that but this has
nothing to do with that. If you mark
anything uh like city property or
private property with uh your you know
paint,
>> right,
>> you're you could be in trouble.
>> But you're not actually tagging
anything.
>> Well, you can I don't know what's the
definition of tagging. I mean, like I'm
not trying to put my identity out there
particularly. Yeah, that's that's the
guy I told you about.
>> Ian and the Pigface Guy are probably
number one and two on uh posting.
>> What annoys you most about this stuff?
It's just dirty.
>> No, no. How would you get to this point?
>> Exactly. Start in city planning. No. Um,
it's a privatization of public space.
The way I see it.
>> To me, they're trying to say, "Well,
this is our space. We're going to use
this and, uh, screw the rest of you."
And I I don't like that attitude.
>> That's you.
>> Well, I'm not going to admit to it, but
see, I could I could probably get uh
arrested for that.
>> Yeah. But
>> graffiti is illegal and if you
participate in it, you're specifically
disregarding the law.
>> And that's a beautiful thing.
>> Graffiti is a way of democratizing the
public space, making it public in a real
way. It's not saying I'm the only one
who gets to do this. It's saying we get
to do this. Anybody can do this. I can't
classify the kind of people who do
graffiti because you got people that do
graffiti that come from good homes. You
got people that do graffiti that's
homeless, that's drug addicts. You got
people that do graffiti that's trying to
do it for the money. You got people that
do graffiti that's for the fame. You got
people that call theirel taggers. You
got people that call piecers. I don't
know what the [__] I am. I'm just going
to say I'm a contributor.
>> My worldview is through the eyes of a
graffiti writer. I felt like I was
finding my identity while I was doing
it.
>> It's a very basic [music]
drive. It's a very basic need to be part
of things to engage with one's world.
>> I really wanted to be part of the
infrastructure.
I feel like writers are very responsible
people because they're pointing out
where there could be art, where there
should be messages.
>> The fun of graffiti is not just the art
itself, but it's the art in the
environment. And it's seeing how the
graffiti writer takes advantage of the
unique characteristics [music] of
wherever they're painting.
>> I'm definitely motivated by like coming
off humorous or bizarre. I've never
wanted to paint things where it like
builds up a personality of trying to be
super tough. I definitely always wanted
to be up but let you know that things
can be funny and you can have a good
time with graffiti.
>> For me, it's always felt rad, like a
communication thing. When I get [__]
just bored or not know what to do with
myself, I'll just leave the house and
walk from Brooklyn all the way through
Manhattan and back again. Come back at
like 5:00 a.m. and leaving all those
notes out there. It's like saying hi to
people. What up? Just the flow of
everything. Just the way the paint
flares when I'm hitting up with a fat
cap or a phantom. Just like [music] a
kinetic energy. So that's like my
ultimate hot, you know, cuz I don't get
hot. I don't drink. I don't smoke. And
never done that [__] in my life.
>> Graffiti is therapeutic.
And sometimes people have to do graffiti
to work things out. And you have to be
free to create without restraint.
Sometimes I'm painting for everybody
who's got to go to work every day and
everybody who sees the same boring walls
just to splash a little bit of mysticism
in there just to snap people out of
their routine. Maybe we're more [music]
free than we thought.
>> It's more than free. It's like it's an
art form that hasn't been tampered with
by people who are [__] trying to make
money off everything. So, it's true.
It's the same as it was when it started.
It was all about getting up and being
individual and being original. I never
got into graffiti to be some like
Picasso. Like, I got into graffiti to
write on [__] and to [__] be a vandal
and be like a [__] kid and be free.
And I guess some people like to look at
boring ass walls. Like they just like to
look they like bor like they're bored.
Like they're boring ass people. Like
think about New York with no graffiti.
It's [__] a boring looking ass place.
>> I do it because I like my work to be in
front [music] of people. It's not about
legal or illegal. It's about no barriers
between the public and the art. It's
it's about populism. I no longer
subscribe to this notion that there's
the [music] good graffiti and the bad
graffiti. There's nothing like seeing an
amazing tag because what you're really
looking at is an amazing piece of
calligraphy. The reason I respect a
seemingly simplistic graffiti tag is
because I understand what goes into
[music] a seemingly simplistic graffiti
tag. I understand the performance behind
it. For example, you have a sleeves tag
and I could see the sleeves tag in my in
my mind's eye. this non-stop s l eee z
the z coming down into a swirl and I
could see the body movement that went
into it. I could see how sleas had to be
covert when doing this tag on the wall.
I could see the shaking of the can. I
can see sleas in action performing that
tag and it's a beautiful ballet of
graffiti making
>> and just being so focused like oh
there's kind of nothing else in the
world going on in your head other than
where you're at right then cuz there's
no room for anything. We all got mediums
that make us feel better cuz some people
do wheelies on motorcycles. Some
[__] bake cakes and [__] at the
bakery and spray a little whipped cream
and they feel like they artist, you
know, and they feel good about theirel.
So, I mean, it's all about how you
handle life.
>> I love the passion to change your
environment. Without that passion, we
accept what is given to us structurally.
We accept what is given to us
aesthetically and we go to sleep and we
die.
[music]
18th Street. So you got some gang. So we
took a sticker down. So we took another
sticker down here. And then you got
this. This guy's got no skills.
Then if their parents don't stop them,
they did their backpack. They did their
rim. They did their garage. They did
their shoes. They did their pants. And
then they go, if nobody stops them, then
they go down the street. Nobody stops
them. They go to the bus line. They go
to the bus benches. They go to the
billboards. So you just follow the trail
back to the house. You talk to them.
When I was growing up, I was from a huge
family and I was like the the the tail
end of all the cousins and my brothers
and all that. So I was like the last one
in line. Oh, you wait your turn.
Everyone roadblocks you. No, you can't
have that. And so plus I was smaller. So
it was a household in an environment
where it was massively competitive, but
nobody ever talked about losing
anything.
Okay. I like run three or four square
miles of the city of Los Angeles. I I
actually think I run that [__] The city
and county spend almost $2 million. I
can take care of graffiti in that same
area for 15,000.
So, see that's going to show up now.
See, when they use acrylics,
>> you can just knock it down with this.
So, we're going to do now is use my
chemical. We'll get rid of that
yellow layers off. And that's it. Nine
times out of 10, I'll have you paint
your own graffiti down. See, you're
already starting to laugh. You think
that's a funny story. And then I I have
gangs actually come out here and help me
paint their own [__] down. If you're a
Latino person walking by this alley,
here's Latino gang threats. Let's say
the guy that wrote that stuff is sitting
right there. Let's say you think it's
really cool to have a bald head. But the
problem is when you're walking by this
and this guy thinks you're with them,
he's going to shoot you. So the same guy
with the same guy walking by with no
graffiti won't say anything to him.
That's how weird it is. That's how weird
this whole business is.
>> When they paint it out, the city paints
like this
>> and they make your tag bigger. rather
than blocking in. It's like they're so
stupid.
>> My god. Are you serious?
>> I mean, this is just crazy, man.
>> You take care of these, too.
>> Yeah. I mean, come on.
>> Why can't Why can't they have something
up that might be important?
>> Yeah, it is important. I'm sure.
>> Most of these things, lost dogs and all
that. If the dog's not bad, brought back
in 3 weeks, the dog's gone. Ain't coming
back. Wow. Now, you tell me what you
think looks better. Tell me what you
think looks better. All that [__] or
that?
>> These guys all run out of Melrose. See,
now another sticker on top of a sticker.
So, I'm going have to go talk to my boys
at KOG and tell them they can't put
their [__] up in my area anymore.
>> No.
Ah, take the color out.
>> Chaka. Oh my god. From his art show.
This is my boy Chaka.
>> Uh, that was I was at that art show.
He's got good stickers. He's not
supposed to be doing this in violation
of his parole. So, I'm actually now
saving him from being arrested by taking
his sticker down. Look how long this
takes. You see, better than a can of
spray paint, right?
>> I know they're going to keep putting
graffiti up. It's an addiction. They're
not going to stop. I mean, I don't care
about the graffiti vandalism. To me,
it's maybe kind of in a weird kind of
way. It's I can't do it. So, maybe by
associating with it, it's me vicariously
living through them. But, um I would
never vandalize someone's property.
When when Fred Radkkey uses the great
paint, he's he's marking his territory.
You know, he's making himself the the
greatest tagger in New Orleans. And
[music] you know, this it's a shame he
doesn't have more talent because he
definitely gets up more than anybody
else.
>> I like to see the gray on me because I
know that there's no graffiti out there
once we get done.
>> This isn't just him painting over
graffiti anymore. He told me that all
the kids that do graffiti are completely
irresponsible. They're degenerates. They
have no hope. They're druggies. That
he's tried. That there's no way to
reform these kids.
>> And not only do drugs, they can actually
once they run out of drugs, they could
rob tourists walking by. There's a hotel
down the street.
>> I run out of drugs. I'll go to Fred's
house cuz I heard he's got a shitload of
them. I got no problem with Buff. But
this guy, man, he's on he's on one.
>> Doing the word top mob is terrorism.
It's not art. I looked over here and I
saw some graffiti back here and I saw
this dude painting over it and I'm like,
"Holy [__] dude. Is that the great
ghost?" I hear some maniac running up on
me. Get the [__] out of here. What the
[__] So, I turn around. I'm just like,
"Whoa, cool, man. I'm gone, dude." And I
try to like walk out of here. Comes up
to me with this paint roll and starts
trying to like paint my hair or paint my
head. He wasn't trying to like hit me at
first. Like, I'm kind of blocking it
over here. And by then, he's already
like started to like hit me on the head
with this paint roll and he caught me
right back here. Big old gash mark in my
head. I didn't realize until he drove
off and I'm drenched in blood. I'm like,
"Wow, wait, that guy really is a
complete psychopath."
>> He'll take a a TV crew out with him from
one of the local stations and then talk
about how, you know, graffiti has
tripled and sometimes it's in the last
year and sometimes it's in the last 10
years. It's whatever number he's he's
pulling out of his butt.
>> But what you have over there is graffiti
has tripled.
>> I would love to see, you know, his his
quantitative statistics on that. down
65% overall in the city, 85% in the
French Quarter.
>> I did a little research on him
afterwards and uh came to find out that
he's a marine and he fought in Desert
Storm. If you're trained by the military
to kill people, hitting somebody with a
paint roller could be considered assault
with a deadly weapon. Anytime I'd go to
the precinct or the courthouse and try
to ask for something, as soon as I walk
in the door, they just kind of be like,
"Who's this kid? What does he want?" I
had the police report and everything.
I'm like, "Hey, is there anything going
on with this?" And they're like, "Oh
yeah, you know, we're looking into it.
what we're investigating. And I
shouldn't have said anything about the
gray ghost cuz I think that might have
turned him off to it being that he's a
friend of the city. I I don't know what
I don't know what Ghost is. I don't know
why he does what he does. He's bored.
Wants to be a hero. Um
doesn't have any friends.
>> Okay. [music]
Okay.
>> At first, I wasn't sure. Um it's a
story, but not, you know, a great story.
And so, I wasn't really excited about
it.
>> Okay. [music]
But then when I started to learn more
about it, when you guys started telling
me more about it, then turned out to be
a great story.
[music]
Well, Sharp was definitely uneasy when I
first talked to him. You know, he said
right off the bat, "Well, I don't want
to admit to anything about spray
painting Berkeley silver." And in the
end, I mean, he was fully admitting that
he was involved. He was kind of proud of
it, really. I get a thrill out of
changing behavior, I guess, to in a in
what I regard a positive way.
>> What would you say to people who said
that you're doing the same thing, sort
of doing your personal mark on the
street and making it private in your
way?
>> Well, I'm not trying to I'm trying to
see I think it you know, if you walk
down the street, there's all this
information bombarding you and and to me
it's this is more more noise. I'd rather
have less noise. It's visual noise. I
think that's pretty clear that Jim Sharp
has only made the graffiti and tagging
problem worse in Berkeley.
>> Honestly, it's bad for the city cuz it
makes you think more diabolical. You're
like, "All right, well, if he's going to
buff every [__] news stand, let's go
hit all the windows down shaded." And
then you hit all the windows and he
can't [__] write silver over it. For
the city, I would think about how it
could escalate into more vandalism.
Talking to the city of Berkeley and the
Berkeley Police Department, I don't
think they're interested in graffiti at
all. They couldn't really care about
graffiti. That it's not a priority for
them whatsoever. And so, by extension,
Jim Sharp and his vigilanteism against
graffiti also wasn't interesting to
them.
>> You're not going to stand.
>> Oh, yeah. Just, you know,
>> on camera.
>> Hey, I don't care about the camera.
>> You're doing You're doing
>> You know what? You keep on holding that
thing up. I'm going to smack you out of
your head one of these days. All right.
You're getting recorded here.
>> You want to leave?
>> You should be smarter than that.
>> Yeah.
>> What do you think of the article?
>> Uh, well, I have a new name for you
guys. Okay.
>> Who are we?
>> Documentarians. I actually thought the
newspaper did a fairly bad job. I was
kind of painted as a as a painter,
right? And that's a really small part of
what I what I do in the mornings.
>> Yeah.
>> Gutters, you know, that's like number
one. Remember this one?
>> What's it?
>> Uh, ethicus. What was it?
>> Erhearta erecta.
>> That's right. It's also called stebans
grass. You both have an eye for detail,
right? I think you'd make pretty good uh
weed abaders or
>> you want to turn us into evaders. Max.
>> Yeah.
>> He sees us as a possible abatement tree.
>> Well, I mean, it takes it takes an eye
to see things, right?
>> You know, Jim, we we do respect your
passion completely. We respect your
dedication, but you've gotten out of
control.
>> And you're the you're the police now,
right? Well,
>> you're the de facto police.
Hey,
>> no, we're just other citizens who have a
perspective and we can be heard and we
can make a movie and be heard that way.
>> Well, yeah, but who's going to see your
movie? Who's going to care
>> if it's a city zoning announcement?
>> And you don't you don't look around at
all like the spray paint that that that
you know over the years the the silver
boxes and the silver stuff and feel a
little bit bad about that.
>> Uh I think I would do some things a
little differently. Black I think works
better in some surfaces than than
silver. But if I had just two colors to
work with, that's probably what I you
know, I think that makes some sense. I
know.
>> Doesn't that just look like a terrible
mess to you?
>> Yeah, it does. It calls attention to it,
saying, "Clean me up." And I'd like to
see somebody come in the next day or
week and paint it the right color.
>> Right.
>> If there was one of us, like a youngster
or youth person or somebody or like a
true tagger or a writer doing that,
houses would get raided, [__] would get
stolen, fools would be going to jail,
court dates, all that stuff would
follow. The fact that he can do what
he's doing with impunity and no one
stopping him. I just think that speaks
to the sickness of American society and
a lot of the injustice that takes place.
I mean, it's crazy. I heard this one kid
getting eight years for tagging.
>> Tears of remorse did not stop a judge
from handing out 8 years in prison to
18-year-old Sebastian Bettis.
>> Why do you pick on these other fine
citizens? Why don't you knock yourself
out spraying, tagging, marking on your
girlfriend's house, her mother's house,
your friend's house, Miss White's house,
your mother's house. Knock yourself out.
You will serve each count, each sentence
consecutive. One ends, you start the
next. The next one ends, you start the
next.
and we will see how good you are on your
promises of wanting to reform your life.
>> He's going to go to prison with the
murders, uh, the robbers, and the real
gangsters. And so, for this little
kindergarten crime that they commit now,
he better learn how to be a man real
quick.
>> A lot of the drive to eliminate graffiti
comes from a fear of youth. I think
there's a sort of fear of the thuggish
element of youth culture and people
somehow associate graffiti with
thuggishness.
>> Nobody. Nobody.
>> Hey mother, look at the artist doing his
art. THAT BEAUTIFUL MOTHER.
>> People respond to graffiti based on what
films say about graffiti or what others
in their community say about graffiti or
what the local news says about graffiti.
But individuals, they don't take the
time to really understand what the
actual graffiti marking or painting is
doing socially for or to a community.
The problem is they only see the
graffiti as contributing to social ills.
>> I wish both the graffiti world and the
street art world would understand kind
of the politics of what they're doing
just in the act of creating street art
or graffiti. You know, the fact that
they are creating some sort of protest
with their actions that this is a form
of property disobedience. In doing so,
they're questioning property laws and
ownership and all of those things and
who has the right to use public space.
>> As the economy has changed, so has the
way in which we understand graffiti.
Find the neighborhood with the most
graffiti in New York or Los Angeles. And
you're probably going to find
neighborhoods where it's a good idea to
seek out cultural attractions, things to
do at night, seek out the best food,
seek out the most diversity. If you see
graffiti, what you're probably seeing is
a neighborhood that is active.
>> Some graffiti is done with no more
thought than to mess things up and cause
a nuisance. That doesn't represent the
whole of graffiti. There's still a lot
of it out there that is done with care
and intention of making things better.
>> Well, I go over corporate signage period
all all the time. There's a company
called MPA City Outdoor and they operate
what are called street level billboards
and they've failed to get permits uh
through the department of buildings and
therefore every location that they
operate is illegal. The NISAD project
was destructive, right? So we went out
and we took back 120 billboards. We
basically destroyed that property.
I mean the company obviously got us
arrested. The people sat in jail for the
weekend and then when they're they had
to come in for court for their court
date, the company again wasn't there.
They didn't want to have to explain to
the judge, yes, they were operating, you
know, illegal signage in the city.
>> It's funny that we just sort of think
it's okay for large corporations to
bombard our visual landscape with their
advertising, but we're so riled up by
seeing a [snorts] tag on the side of the
wall, even a beautiful colorful piece on
a wall. Many people find that very
offensive. You don't necessarily have to
consume what is being advertised, but to
understand that advertising plays a
significant role in society and speaks
to our culture and speaks for our
culture in many ways, you have to
respect advertising on that level. Same
with graffiti.
>> Advertising is meant to manipulate you
and that's all it's there for. And
people don't see that. They don't see
that as being a problem. One of the
things I find really interesting about
people's responses to outdoor
advertising is this consistent
explanation that they don't look at it,
that they don't see it. I find in that
statement a huge problem, people having
to ignore their space while they walk
through it or consciously ignoring it,
right? I mean, what a terrible way to
have to move through something that
should be considered yours.
It's one of the things I really love
about public works, street art, and
graffiti in general is that there's so
many contradictions. The public is made
of so many different people with so many
different opinions who whose opinions
are all valid, right? We all occupy the
space. We all pay our taxes. We all have
a right to our own opinion about it. And
so, you do have to kind of negotiate
everybody's interests in this
environment. And those interests often
collide and do not line up perfectly. I
think these buffers are on the wrong
side. I think they should be getting rid
of the advertising.
>> I look at this maybe in 1995 this would
have pissed me off. She's being
controlled by graffiti. No, I'm
controlling graffiti. Let them try to
control me and they won't control me.
You know why? Cuz I respect them. But
now it's like I don't I don't I see
doesn't even bother me. I'm okay with
your rebellion because I I I mean I'm
really extremely rebellious. I hate
authority. I don't I don't do good with
authority. I mean, I only seem to do
good with dogs and kids. And I side more
on the side of taggers and and people
outside the box than I do people that
are inside the box in the corporate
world. They've done nothing but take
advantage of me my whole life. A lot of
my feistiness really comes from my
grandmother. Man, I love my grandma. My
grandmother was like, man, meant the
world to me. So, go
>> She passed away in um 1999.
And then 40 days later, 35 days later,
whatever that was, then we lost Adam.
And then over the next four or five
years, it was,
you know, brothers, father, cousins, my
first business mentor, just it was for
me, it was just I had to find a way to
survive and and try to try to channel
all that anxiety into something. And so,
it's not only about the control, it's
really the power to make myself better.
And so by controlling it, I I actually
maybe I'm deliluding myself into
thinking I'm I'm making it better, but
I'm also being positive. My boy Dale of
BK gone. Now I'll go next time I see
him, I'll tell Dale, seriously, tagging
Charles Jr. at the writer's bench. And
he'll say, "Wow, man, you found that?
That's that's that's dope, man. Don't be
doing that [__] Why can't you leave my
[__] up, dude?"
>> You know, so we uh it's like, you know,
so do I get angry? No. It's like fun and
games. It's fun and games.
So I don't give a [__] I like your
attitude.
You're right.
[music]
>> I want to
know.
[music]
I want to
know. Graffiti gorilla OG. That's what's
up. That's That's what's up. I ain't
[__] around. You know, I'm probably
the only buffer who likes graffiti art.
I mean like totally I mean like get
people jobs.
>> No. So you know but like if somebody
[__] at me I just put a line through
their name. I write 18 Street like oh
>> So what would it take for you to stop?
>> What why do you ask that question?
Because
I'd like you to stop.
>> Why? Why would you like me to stop?
>> Cuz I think you're
>> It might say something about you which I
don't think you want anybody to know
about.
>> I think you're suppressing free speech
here. You don't have to do this every
day. Maybe you could do it.
>> Free speech.
>> This is free speech.
>> If you if you consider it,
>> it's you you'll notice that free speech
has two sides to it.
Your kind of free speech is is the
speech that suppresses other people's
ability to speak. It's not the same
thing.
>> Well, it's a philosophical difference we
have. I guess
>> there's been a vigilante loose on the
streets of Berkeley since the early 90s.
In his overzealous pursuit of
eliminating illegal markings, Sharp has
become the most prolific graffiti vandal
the city has ever seen. Indiscriminately
tearing down legally placed posters
nearly every morning, whether they be
for events, lost pets, missing children,
etc., Sharp acts as a street sensor,
blocking the flow of grassroots
information. We humbly ask the city
council and community of Berkeley to be
aware of Jim Sharp's actions and to come
together to stop his obsessive
vandalism. He is a menace to the
community fabric.
>> There certainly have been many
conversations about this. So it's not
that nothing,
it's just in Berkeley there is a lot of
talk and not much action on many
subjects. In my conversations with him,
he seems to be absolutely convinced that
you know what he's doing is noble and
you know that we should be praising him
and rewarding him for what he's doing.
>> Can you still get the kids here? I guess
you get rid of this stuff then then it
becomes sort of a useless.
You can't get in touch with
>> unless you get rid of the phone number.
>> Yeah.
>> I'm not going to be driving around in a
in a Joe Connelly uh van with all the
all the different colors.
>> But it's it's it's like individual
letters, you know. Now, you don't know
whether it's a dot or or a.com. So,
>> when I explain to him that what he's
doing is actually ethically and legally
very challenged behavior,
you know, he doesn't seem to take that
seriously. Well, I'm very sorry for your
documentary. If me as just one council
member saying that I'm concerned about
it is all you're getting from the city,
that's pretty sad.
>> What is around here?
>> He does all that up there. Oh, he a
silver B.
>> [music]
>> Just cuz it's silver doesn't even mean
it's mine. Did your either one of you
take a philosophy course? Any course in
philosophy?
>> Once upon a time. Yeah.
>> Okay. Ordinary language analysis is a
good start.
>> And if you see a herd of sheep and
they're sheared
>> Yes. How would the ordinary language and
analyst look at that? They're sheared on
this side. That's all. They don't know
that they're sheared on the opposite
side of the shoe,
>> right?
>> So, just because this is silver doesn't
mean that I did it. This is Is this your
Valentine?
>> I think you're going to be in deep [__]
>> Since this guy is going to block his P.
>> How was Ste?
Yeah. Illegal surface.
>> Oh, hey. I haven't touched your
property.
>> Yeah. Well, what what's your property
doing all over the place?
>> Staying on.
I'm uh otherwise known as Bishop Joey in
a church that I created called the first
church at the last laugh which has
sponsored since 1979 a parade in San
Francisco called the St. Day parade held
every April 1st. I kept noticing other
religious stickers around town and
decided I wanted to to get in on that. I
consider it a type of graffiti that's uh
considerate. I put them in public
property or on somebody's advertising. I
am on a mission. You know, I'm trying to
subvert the dominant religious
paradigms. Uh uh I do political satire
with the mime troop and I do religious
satire with St. Steen. I love looking at
graffiti, you know. I just love seeing
the different styles. I think it's it's
it's art. It's folk art in the street.
It's a shout of here I am. It's a shout
of I exist. More important that these
kids say something, have their ability
to walk by a wall, you know, in an alley
and go that's my tag. They feel there's
an empowerment to that. I've seen grown
up. I've done grown up. [__] that [__]
You know, [laughter]
for Jim, it's he's got a little control.
He sees this as noise. He's against it.
He's eradicated it. He's done something.
It's just the opposite of that little
kid with the the marker going, putting
his scrawl up. You know, he's he sees
the noise around him. He's added his
voice to the noise. He's added his
sound. It's nice having a, you know, an
antagonist, you know, because I'll be
I'll be looking for him and my dream,
Jim, my dream is to be following you,
you know, and you'll be scraping a
sticker, you know, and then I'll be
right behind you putting up a new one.
[laughter]
>> When you see him,
>> look at all the silver.
>> Yeah,
>> that looks like [__]
>> [__] up the whole neighborhood here.
>> He needs to be trained. I have to train
him.
>> So, Mr. Sharp, good morning. Joe Connley
from Los Angeles. Well, it is a it is a
pleasure.
>> You should be wearing a slicker. Do
people bug you about the paint? Why
silver?
>> These guys These guys
>> No, I'm I'm just curious.
>> Uh silver is a very good cover up. Uh I
I don't have a truck with a lot of
different paints in it as apparently you
do. But
>> no, I just went out because people will
start saying, "You're an [__] You
don't match the paint."
>> No, no, I get that.
>> Jim's eventually maybe going to figure
it out that he's going to match all this
paint. Then he's going to meet these
little [__] and he's going to say
stop. And they'll stop because they they
have they they need that. They're
addicted. They're addicted. Like the
guys with the posters are, they all have
their own because that's the money.
>> Are you guys Are you guys addicted
though? Are
>> I'm addict Oh, I'm Yeah, I'm massively
addicted.
>> Every time they find somebody that's
doing some abatement work,
>> you basically
>> community activism.
>> I know. You you you make them out to be
a fanatic,
>> right?
>> But you know what? We are a little
fanatical. I mean, I'm I'm I'm probably
I'm probably as I mean, the reason why a
lot of guys leave me alone in LA is
because they know
>> I'm probably more obsessed than they
are.
>> Wow.
>> That silver.
>> But look at this, Jim.
>> So, so the silver buff there.
>> It's a balance.
>> Someone's taunting you. It's all talking
back and forth each other. There's our
boy. He may not like
>> But Jim, but why why not? Why not the
tape?
>> That's just your
>> Well, I'm I'm I'm distracted.
>> I'm just I'm just saying. But you leave
this. Then you left all those stickers
on the window. You left that thing over
there. And you left these things over
here. See, you got to know how to rush.
So that's the crazy thing about this is
we all get blamed for graffiti and the
consequences of it because we just
standing trying to catch a bus
sometimes. So see they they'll say, "Oh,
she with gangster pimp play,
you know, and it boom boom boom, you
know." Well, come on.
>> What do you think of Joe so far?
>> He's he's he's even more than I
imagined. If you [__] don't
leave Jim Jerry alone, I'm [__]
coming up here and it's going to be some
[__]
>> Fred Radkkey tried to have me cited with
1,500 counts or something of illegally
posting on telephone polls. It was going
to be like $50,000 in fines. When I
first noticed that my signs were being
painted over with with the gray paint,
they were street signs. It's like weird,
you it's helping people get around the
city cuz the city didn't have enough
money to put up a street sign. So, I got
this really badass civil rights
attorney. It went down at one count and
a $200 fine with just like, you know, 6
months of no posting on telephone polls.
I learned a valuable lesson. You know,
don't sign your artwork with your real
name. [music]
People write stuff up on the walls like
no more [music] ghosting, the whole
Ghostbusters emblem.
You had these Fred says stencils,
you know, you had art reaction to them.
When Binksy got to town, he was informed
about the battle going on between myself
and Mr. Ratkkey and the riders in town.
Now, Mr. Ratkkey was responsible for
buffing out some of the pieces that
Banksy had put up. One of the news
stations had gotten it on film and put
it on one of their news segments.
>> The recent works of worldrenowned artist
Banksy have taken street art to a new
level.
>> Have you ever covered over any of his
stuff?
>> No.
>> But has anybody asked you to do that?
>> I I've read it has been covered, but
people know me. If I'm going to cover up
something, it's not going to be just a
flower or just a little boy. It's going
to be everything.
>> I think for Mr. Radkkey to say that he
hasn't painted over a Banky piece is a
bit of an erroneous statement.
>> So the owners of this wall gave
permission to a bunch of local artists
to paint on it. And uh originally it was
this beautiful thing that said welcome
to the by water and RKI came by and
started graying over it. Uh completely
ruined the piece. The owners of the wall
found out. They had the artist come back
out and paint another piece. Started to
gray over that and they decided to take
matters into their own hands. They ended
up having to call the military police
who um arrested Raki.
>> This person that has this mural, it's
illegal. Okay. No one said anything
about this mural. It's illegal. The
graffiti taggers got permission from the
property owner. That's okay. The point
making is the property owner did get
permission from the city of New Orleans.
>> Did you get a court order to not paint
on buildings?
>> I didn't get any court order. I was
asked by the court not to paint on
buildings without permission from a
property owner. Did you paint on
somebody's building today without
permission?
>> If we did, we weren't aware of it.
>> Are you in violation of of the court?
What happened in,
>> you know, because did they tell you to
get permission before?
>> I don't know. I mean, a lot of what I
think the buffers get into is that they
immediately have a label for it that
calls it a bad thing or calls it gang
stuff. One of the things that society
needs to learn is to get past that
narrow misconception. There's more out
there than gangbangers just out [__]
up [__] And that's where the perception
is.
>> You got over a dozen formats of people
doing graffiti ranging from satonic cult
to hiphop gang.
>> He doesn't know what he's dealing with.
I don't think he's ever really met a
graffiti writer. When I was a kid, I'd
see it on the wall and I'd be like,
"Man, that's awesome." You know, you get
to draw on the walls.
It's a renaissance era right now with
graffiti out here and just art in
general.
We're We're stepping it up. All the
other artists are stepping it up. We're
building. Our city was pretty destroyed,
but you know, we're starting over.
Hopefully, we can do something that you
can love. Some people are going to hate.
That sucks. Oh well.
A lot of these gray buffs are uh they
hit close to home.
>> There's no winner [music] cuz no matter
what, at the end of the day, shit's
going to get buffed.
>> You're going to go over me. I'm just
persistent as you, old man. I'm a
[music] little bit younger than you. I
wasn't a Marine or nothing and I'm not
the best [music] fighter, but I got a
heart.
[music]
Make sure there's no cops around cuz
this is illegal.
>> The petetroglyphic stupid.
>> I hear you've been following me around.
>> You're this guy.
>> I'm this guy.
>> Oh yeah. Wait, you got the t-shirt?
>> Yeah.
>> While you're doing it though, can you
consider taking down the other stuff?
>> You want me to take it down?
>> Well, in front of you, I mean, like I'm
kind of awed by the whole experience
here.
>> Well, here take
>> Here's what I would do ordinarily.
>> Okay. You got a job, Jim. You got a job.
Me, too. See,
>> why even bother scraping a sticker off,
though? Now you know him. Now he's your
friend. Why would you do that?
>> Well, I we're not friends. We're
>> Yeah, I was I was Mr. Madam Mayor for
one of them. I remember that. Yeah.
>> Well, it's uh Can I put a sticker in
your bucket?
>> Well, I don't collect them. All right.
That's I guess I should I'll try to keep
that forever, but right. Good luck. It's
nice to meet you, Jim.
>> Yeah. I'll see you around. Okay. Uh, it
would be hard to picture Berkeley
without graffiti, but
>> I mean, in a in a sense though,
Berkeley's graffiti gives you sort of a
of a of a reason to be doing what you're
doing.
>> Well,
>> even though a lot of the graffiti in
Berkeley is technically yours.
[laughter]
I mean,
>> well, what are we going to do? What? We
need our definitions. Get those down.
>> I mean, graffiti is any marking that you
put up on a public service without
without permission.
Uh
that's that's one definition if you want
to use that one.
Have you ever had the pleasure of
breaking a window on building?
>> No, I don't break windows. I'm a window
saver.
>> You've never broken a window on purpose?
>> No.
>> When I'm asked if graffiti is an attack
on society, I say, of course, it's an
attack on society. But first, you have
to define what you mean by society. If
society is a system of private property
ownership and exclusion. If society is a
system of laws that are largely drawn up
by real estate investors, private
property owners, a government who
subscribes to a system of capitalism and
colonialism and war. If society is a
system of undermining the perspective of
young people, then I'm very much in
favor of graffiti not being part of that
society and in fact destroying those
elements of that society.
>> If you believe in the way things are and
that they should keep continuing as they
are, then you would see graffiti as
going against something you believe in.
Whether or not you understand it in
those terms, I can see why it would make
you angry. I think America is all about
hiding the expenses. just hiding the
fact that we're [__] things up and
taxing the world.
>> When I talk to people about why they
don't like graffiti, usually it just has
to do with they don't like looking at
it. They think it looks ugly. Well,
okay, that's unfortunate, but it's not a
serious crime. You have a giant ship,
the the USS Los Angeles, and you have
holes in its hole, and you're a
politician and you know that you can't
fill all of those holes in the hole.
What do you do? You paint the ship and
you tell everyone it looks good and it's
staying afloat and people believe you.
Why? Because how could a beautiful ship
be sinking? People are so foolish when
it comes to appearances. They really
believe that making things look good
makes them work better.
>> We see great disparities in wealth,
reduction in some pretty essential
services, including healthcare and
education. And I think there's been
overemphasis on removing graffiti at the
expense of other more pressing needs.
When you have laws being broken by the
US presidential administration or you
have laws being broken in the form of
stealing money from investors
undermining people's ability to consume
food, housing, and education on a level
that's equal with everyone else in
society, the breaking of those laws is
so sophisticated that individuals and
small groups feel powerless in the face
of the breaking of those laws. Do you
think the graffiti writers may feel
controlled in their lives and that
they're reasserting some control in a
competitive way with the society around
them?
>> I have no idea how graffiti writers feel
in their soul of souls.
>> I think the reason people are so
outraged by the breaking of laws in the
case of graffiti is because they feel
empowered enough to be able to intervene
and challenge the breaking of those
laws. When those people really think
about graffiti, they have to ask
themselves, why am I so outraged by
this? What really happened here today
when that wall was written on? And that
lack of a definite answer leaves people
feeling crazy. And that feeling of
craziness makes people very angry.
Graffiti now is really the start of an
entire demise of an area because in with
it comes homelessness, trash, empty
storefronts, it's broken windows, but
it's broken windows doesn't go far
enough because the people that drove
broken windows don't know a goddamn
thing about graffiti. All the stickers
are off the poles starting to just take
all this whole area back from everybody.
Still some [__] going on. All this
is all tagged up. This was all weeds in
here. So we walked all knocked all this
down. All this stuff will be cut back.
All this stuff will be cut back. This
all these trees will be cleaned up. Like
this this just all went up. See? So
somebody's like somebody's noticing
stuff. So we'll knock that down. Took me
three days to knock everything down here
by myself. There was eight people living
in here. Eight. Sometimes there said do
not no trespassing. They rip those down.
Like there's nowhere for them to stay.
If it rains they get wet.
Hello. Morning.
How's it going, sir? People got to stay
somewhere. But unfortunately now, like I
said, this neighbor wants to take all
this area back. Plus, this is a this is
a fire hazard. I hate
>> you want to cut every bush down around
this [__] Go ahead and knock.
Cuz I'm I just turned 50, man. Look
here. I don't have problem. I've been in
jail. I've been locked up. I ain't [__]
with nobody. You [__] with me. So dog
>> I'm sorry you feel that way.
>> But listen, if animals can stay up in
here, I can.
>> Okay.
>> If dogs and pets can stay up in here, I
can.
>> All right, T. Hey, don't get be careful
out there. Okay,
>> good luck moving all your [__]
>> You know, losing your house is a [__]
Someone take my house, I'd be pissed
off, too.
>> Yeah. Yeah. Compliance is I'm a control
freak. So, see, in a democracy, in my
world, it's easy. You don't have to
think. Just show up. We'll tell you what
to do, and that's it. Cuz why? cuz I
know what I want is what everybody
wants. They're just afraid to say it.
So, I'm I'm okay with that.
>> I'm not a vigilante. The difference is
once you drop off the E, you become the
thing I am, and that's vigilant. And,
you know, I think vigilantes are like a
little edgy, a little crazy.
>> If law enforcement or the city ever
hassled you about painting uh public or
private property, which is technically
illegal,
>> that would be that would be so not in
their best interest to bother me. Have
they ever tried to question you or I
would have to dismiss them.
>> Some gang friends of mine, they're like,
"Hey, Joe, how you doing today?" They
call me cuz you used to watch my sign.
>> And they go, "Uh, you're going to going
to believe this, but right now there's
seven LAPD guys here painting your sign
out." So, I rolled over on my bike and
said, "Sergeant, what are you doing?" He
said, "Well, we got this new captain. He
doesn't like your sign." I go, "Fuck
that son of a [__] Here's what we do.
Drop your [__] guns. I'm a
citizen arresting all you [__]
right now and you're all under arrest."
So, I went down to the station, jumped
over the [__] counter. I said, 'I
want to talk to Captain [__] John
Mutz. So, Captain Mutz had a meeting
with me and he said, 'You know, I found
your sign to be disrespectful. I said, I
find you to be out of your [__] mind.
You're a dumb [__] Gang members
now think I'm a dick cuz of you. So now
I'm picking the gang members over you.
You know why? Cuz only 9,500 of you
[__] are there and there's 100,000
of them. And they got all the guns and
bullets from the riots. So if their war
breaks out, you're gone. You're It's
over for you.
So I'm warning you. You come back. You
can't come back in my neighborhood till
you apologize to me.
>> Some of the people who watch some of
this might just say he's crazy. What
would you tell those people?
>> They're right.
>> Yeah, they're right. You know, I can't
disagree. There's crazy and then there's
Gosh, what's another good descriptive
word for him?
>> He's crazy but not insane.
>> Could you imagine not being able to buff
anymore at a certain age?
>> When would that happen?
>> I'd go to a retirement home. Somebody's
gonna have to push me around in a
wheelchair. So, as long as I can, look
how far, let's say I'm sitting in a
wheelchair. I can come by here like I'm
sitting here like this in a wheelchair.
I could just be like this. I can still
work a knife. I mean, I got two hip
replacements. They said I wouldn't run a
marathon again. I now have more marathon
finishes than anybody anybody in the
history of the city of LA.
>> Could you handle it if you had to stop
buffing for some reason?
>> I I don't see that happening. I deal
with a lot of crazy things and I was
able to make sense out of it. I just go,
you know, get some guys in rehab, go
paint some graffiti, go find a way to
get some guys in art programs. I'd just
keep moving because if I actually stop
to think about it, man, I'd be a mess.
I'd be a total mess.
I'm on the right track and that's all
that matters. That's all that matters to
me. So, I don't care what people think.
You know, life's too short.
You getting this?
>> Yeah, I'm the pink buff and this is the
gold buff. We're going to be buffing all
your buffs.
>> Oh, look. This is This is a vandal.
You guys are doing
>> what? That's vandalism.
>> Yeah.
>> Does that Does that match anything here?
>> Uh,
this silver doesn't seem to match blue,
Jim. I don't know. We're just going to
try to call attention to it. It says
clean me up, you know.
>> This [__] [__]
Don't bring that to anymore. Don't touch
that anymore. Okay.
>> I haven't touched it. You hear me?
>> They're touching.
>> No more.
>> We're trying to take care of him.
>> No. No more paint the This is a city
property. You guys are bad.
>> It's not us, man.
>> Who put the container? He did.
>> He did. I'm going call the cops. You
going to tell the cops that?
>> It's pretty good cover up. [music]
What should I bring when I move to the
sky?
I'll bring everything.
[music] What should I write on my grave
[singing] when I die? [music]
I'll write everything.
Conversation [music]
with God.
There's no one in there.
Everything [music]
must come.
>> You guys are tagging different color
paints along here. I can show you what
where the tags are.
>> Well, somebody called in about you guys
spray painting the uh the trash cans,
and I'm just trying to figure out what
the deal is. And they've today they've
they've brought their own paint and
they're and they're following me around
and painting service. So that's your
tutor.
>> Have you have you not painted services?
>> Not today.
>> You're just calling attention to him
doing this over the the years. Yes.
>> By spray painting yourself. Unbelievable
story. Why don't Let me get some names.
>> There's that. And your ID, sir.
Um, I have a an an expired driver's
license in my book. That's fine. Okay,
just hold on a second. But is it
graffiti if they're covering up real
you answer for all the ones you've done?
>> I'll answer for the ones that are on the
tape that you guys got.
>> So, you'll lie about the so you know
you've done every single one of these
things out here. That's amazing.
>> Yeah. And you don't have cans of paint
today, Jim. Good for you.
>> Smooth move.
>> He was in [__] Did you know that?
>> What?
>> I did this deliberately to get you guys
uh
>> Yeah.
>> Here.
>> Believe it.
>> He didn't actually see anybody spray
painting. So, I'm just going to write it
up as a suspicious circumstance. Ship it
on through. I'm sure what he's telling
me is true. But, you know, until we have
a prosecutable case,
>> the color of the paint because it
>> doesn't matter.
>> Yeah. I guess that's all.
>> So, we can expect to maybe hear back
about this.
>> I can hear back about this.
>> Okay. Well, that's definitely
>> I'll pick up a little garbage.
>> We've been through a lot together.
[music]
>> All [music and singing] our passing f
Stop hating.
Everything must come and go.
>> [music]
>> I'm seeing spaceships.
I'm seeing
[music]
I see. [singing]
I'm trying to figure it all out. [music]
>> [music]
>> I see a murid.
My dad.
[music]
Oh,
hey.
>> [music]
>> Heat. Heat.
Heat. [music]
[music]
Heat.
>> [music]
>> Heat. Heat.
[music]
Heat. Heat. [music]
night.